<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Forrest dream list</title>
    <subtitle>Overview</subtitle>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>
        This is the initial attempt to give focus to the Forrest project. This
        summary is a loose collection of items from the forrest-dev mailing
        list. Please add and re-arrange so that it can evolve into a focus
        document. The <link href="site:primer">Forrest Primer</link> provides an
        overview.
      </p>
      <p>
        These are the email threads and documents that are currently being
        summarised. Please see those documents for further detail.
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
    [RT] my Forrest dream-list
    Date: Wed, 20 Feb 2002
    <link href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101431895118349">http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101431895118349</link>
    [done]
   </li>
        <li>
    README 
    [FIXME: not yet started summarising]
   </li>
        <li>
    [phases] Forrest
    Date: Fri, 22 Feb 2002
    <link href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101445744931104">http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101445744931104</link>
    [FIXME: not yet started summarising]
   </li>
        <li>
    adding to the dream list
    Date: Fri, 15 Mar 2002
    <link href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101620970016263">http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101620970016263</link>
    [FIXME: not yet started summarising]
   </li>
        <li>
    analysis paralysis :-)
    Date: Mon, 25 Feb 2002
    <link href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101465344708301">http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101465344708301</link>
    [FIXME: not yet started summarising]
   </li>
        <li>
    documentation architecture?
    Date: Thu, 25 Apr 2002
    <link href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101973705501466">http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101973705501466</link>
    [FIXME: not yet started summarising]
   </li>
        <li>
    Topic Maps for Forrest ?
    Date: Mon, 18 Mar 2002
    <link href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101647290524645">http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101647290524645</link>
    [FIXME: not yet started summarising]
   </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Draft dream list</title>
      <ul>
        <li>
   Forrest provides a robust technological infrastructure for open software development for the Apache Software Foundation based on ASF software, ASF practices and experience, and modern software design principles.
  </li>
        <li>
  a publishing system for documentation
 </li>
        <li>
  analysis of logs and publishing of results
 </li>
        <li>
Ok, first of all: "it hurts my spirit" (I should TM this) to see the
apache web sites with such a *poor* information infrastructure. Just
look at sourceforge: it's not the best site of the world, but gives you
lots of tools and information that we currently don't have (or have
hidden someplace).
 </li>
        <li>
I want Forrest to be the development infrastructure of your dreams,
something that you'll be proud of showing your boss and say "if only we
had this in place, we would save big bucks" so...
 </li>
        <li>
  Dream #1: Forrest should make Sourceforge look obsolete.
 </li>
        <li>
So, in order for this to happen, it must be dynamic.
Assumption #1: Forrest is a dynamic site.
The staticity of apache web sites was mostly due to the quest for heavy
mirroring, Forrest should allow mirroring, so
 </li>
        <li>
  Dream #2: Forrest should reduce xml.apache.org bandwidth use dramatically
 </li>
        <li>
  Dream #3: Forrest should automate mirroring in a simple and easy way.

My idea is to use the 'command line' features of Cocoon to generate
static snapshots of sites and produce mirrors directly using a sort of
rsync or other mean. Anyway, the goal is to make sure mirroring is as
easy as possible. No, easier than that.
 </li>
        <li>
  coherence: all the site should look coherent, same graphics, same
look-and-feel, same information in the same locations, coherent and nice URI
space (build to last! so that broken links are reduced!)
 </li>
        <li>
  structure: the site should look professional, the structure should be
flexible enough to fit every need but solid enough to guide users
browsing and developers adding resources
 </li>
        <li>
  scalability
 </li>
        <li>
  functionality: everything you ever wanted to have in your project web site
 </li>
        <li>
 logs and community rating: I want to have numbers to judge the value
of a community/effort
 </li>
        <li>
Downloads, number of committers, numbers of people subscribed on the users/dev
list, numbers of mail messages / week on these lists, CVS activity...
These are the kind of parameters I use to "judge" an Apache project that I
have not been looking into before.
 </li>
        <li>
  Graphs of various statistics.
 </li>
        <li>
Having good site metrics will be a valuable aid to those involved in
maintenance and future re-design phases.
See some discussion in
<link href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=102238816218885">http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=102238816218885</link></li>
        <li>
 Built-in search engine: users much have a simple way to find things.
 Lucene.
 </li>
        <li>
 User-writable pages: people should have a way to add things to the pages.
 See the thread for more detail on this.
FIXME: get MARC ref
 </li>
        <li>
 short bios for the project committers, with pictures: gives a better
sense of community. Having a weblog there would be great.
 </li>
        <li>
 news, announcements, events and project calendaring: the news and
the announcements will generate a RSS feed, events will be aggregated
into a project-wide calendar, or an effort-specific calendar, the events
will also be overwritten on the logs, to indicate how logs were
influenced by the events (say, a release or a new committer added)
 </li>
        <li>
 book-like PDF versions of documentation: easy to print out docs.
 </li>
        <li>
  integration with GUMP: dependencies, runs, committer that broke the run
 </li>
        <li>
 javadocs seemlessly integrated with the documentation and with the
search engine.
 <link href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101620970016263">http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=forrest-dev&amp;m=101620970016263</link></li>
        <li>
 mail archive seemlessly integrated with the search engine (one should
look for something and get results from either docs, javadocs or emails
messages)
 </li>
        <li>
  coherent-looking CVS view
 </li>
        <li>
  document translation using Google translation services
 </li>
        <li>
 Integrated project management, task management, bug tracking, feature requests, process management. 
The idea is to integrate Scarab for bug tracking/patches and
managing/feature requests.
(As far as team management, this is a serious political issue and I do not
want to tackle that one yet, not even on the dreamlist.)
 </li>
        <li>
  overview doco for all projects ... CVS Usage precis, overview of opensource
  and links to relevant doco
 </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
