<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE howto PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD How-to V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/howto-v20.dtd">
<howto>
  <header>
    <title>How to customize Forrest CSS 
      WYSIWYG-style</title>
    <abstract>
      This How-To shows how to use Mozilla Firefox and the free EditCSS-Plugin
      to customize your Forrest design in a WYSIWYG-way.
    </abstract>
    <last-modified-content-date date="2004-11-05"/>
  </header>
  <audience title="Intended Audience">
    <p>
      Users who want to customize the Forrest look and feel or simply experiment
      with changing certain CSS-styles settings to see what happens.
    </p>
  </audience>
  <purpose title="Purpose">
    <p>
      A major part of Forrest's look and feel is controlled by a few CSS style
      sheets. Since Forrest allows you to override these settings, changing the
      CSS is a quick and easy alternative to creating (and maintaining) a whole
      new skin.
    </p>
    <p>
      You'll learn how to use free tools to change and experiment with styles in
      a WYSIWYG way, so that you can immediately see what effect changing a CSS
      property will have on the look and feel of your Forrest.
    </p>
  </purpose>
  <prerequisites title="Prerequisites">
    <p>
      To follow these instructions you will need:
    </p>
    <ol>
      <li>Browser-access to the Forrest-site you want 
        to experiment with. Starting with a new 'forrest seed' site is
        good for your first attempt.
        <note>
          You can even experiment with Forrest's core skins CSS. Please send
          patches if you enhance something.
        </note></li>
      <li>The current version of the free Mozilla 
        Firefox-Browser installed on your system. 
        If you don't already use it, you can 
        download it from <a 
        href="http://www.mozilla.org/products/firefox/">http://www.mozilla.org/products/firefox/</a></li>
      <li>The Firefox-PlugIn EditCSS. It downloads 
        and installs in just a few seconds from the 
        Install-Link at <a 
        href="http://editcss.mozdev.org/">http://editcss.mozdev.org/</a>
        <note>
          With standard security settings in place, Firefox will pop up a line
          at the top of the window because this site has by default no
          permission to install plugins on your computer. Click "Edit Options"
          and then "Allow" to change that, then click on the Install-link again.
          Don't forget to close and restart Firebird when the installation is
          finished.
        </note></li>
      <li>A basic understanding of CSS and access to 
        a good CSS-reference. Tutorials and 
        Reference can be found at <a 
        href="http://www.htmlhelp.com/reference/css/">http://www.htmlhelp.com/reference/css/</a>.</li>
    </ol>
  </prerequisites>
  <steps title="Steps">
    <section id="openForrest">
      <title>Open your Forrest</title>
      <p class="instruction">
        Start your Firefox Browser and open the Forrest you'd like to work
        on/play with.
      </p>
      <p>
        The page you have pointed to will show up in Firefox's main window.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="OpenEditCSS">
      <title>Open the EditCSS-Sidebar</title>
      <p class="instruction">
        Select View-Sidebar-EditCSS from Firefox's main menu to open the EditCSS
        sidebar.
      </p>
      <p>
        The EditCSS sidebar will show next to the main window and load all the
        styles from the main page.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="changeCSS">
      <title>Change any CSS</title>
      <p class="instruction">
        Change any style you'd like to experiment with or add new settings and
        styles of your choice by simply editing the text of the sidebar.
      </p>
      <p>
        EditCSS pushes any change you make in the sidebar right back into the
        style-settings of the main window, so that effects will show right away.
      </p>
      <note>
        On slow systems or when inserting big changes it might be a good idea to
        paste these from the clipboard to avoid a zillion updates to the main
        windows for every character you type.
      </note>
    </section>
    <section id="saveChanges">
      <title>How to save changes?</title>
      <p>
        Since it takes a few explanations to apply the changes to your Forrest,
        I've made this the topic of yet another HowTo called "Howto change and
        extend Forrest-CSS"
      </p>
    </section>
  </steps>
  <feedback 
    title="Feedback and further development of this How-To">
    <p>
      Please provide feedback about this document via the
      <a href="site:mail-lists">mailing lists</a>.
    </p>
  </feedback>
</howto>
