<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v12.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Overview of the How-To documents</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Forrest Site and Documentation</title>
      <ul>
        <li><link href="site:write-howto">How to write a How-To</link>
          - Provides instructions about writing documents. Please copy this
          file to serve as a template for your own document.
        </li>
        <li><link href="site:asf-mirror">Generate an ASF mirrors page using interactive web form</link>
          - include html form elements
          into a forrest-generated html page. For example, this enables building
          automated download mirror pages for ASF project websites.
          Also shows how to process "extra" documents, i.e. that have no links
          from anywhere in the site.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Using and developing with Forrest</title>
      <p>
        You will soon see that there is not much distinction between users and
        developers.
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li><link href="site:pdf-tab">How to create a PDF document for each tab</link>
          - Describes the generation of a PDF document for each
          group of documents that is defined by a tab.
        </li>
        <li><link href="site:editcss">How to edit Forrest's CSS in a WYSIWYG fashion</link>
          - Describes the use of Mozilla Firebird and the free EditCSS-Plugin to 
          customize your Forrest design in a WYSIWYG-way.
        </li>
        <li><link href="site:corner-css">How to modify the color of generated corner images</link>
          - Describes the use of CSS values from the skinconf.xml configuration
          file to change the color of the corner images to be suitable for
          your own skin colors. Advanced use explains editing the *.css too.
        </li>
        <li><link href="site:maven">How to run Forrest from within Maven</link>
        - For Maven users who want to generate their project's documentation and/or website
          using Forrest in lieu of Maven's site plugin.
        </li>
        <li><link href="site:custom-html-source">How to customize processing of html source</link>
        - When integrating legacy html documents into a Forrest-built site, additional processing
        of the html sources might be required.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Extending Forrest</title>
      <ul>
        <li><link href="site:buildPlugin">How to create a Plugin for Forrest</link>
          - Describes how to write a plugin to add new input or output document
          formats, or to modify the default behaviour of Forrest</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
